Finding Aid of the Halleck, Peachy & Billings Records
Halleck, Peachy & Billings Records,
1842-1862
2030
Halleck, Peachy & Billings (Firm)
7 boxes (3.5 linear ft.) 1 carton (1 linear ft.)
University of California, Los Angeles. Library. Department of Special Collections. Los Angeles, California 90095-1575
Halleck, Peachy & Billings was one of the leading San Francisco law firms in the settlement of titles to Mexican land grants. The firm was dissolved in 1861. The collection contains correspondence, mainly relating to land litigation of Halleck, Peachy & Billings, with documents and diseños (originals, copies, and translations) used in the settlement of the claims. Also contains papers in various legal cases, some concerning ships, Chinese immigration and the San Francisco funding bill, as well as a few accounts and some tax records.
Administrative Information
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library, Department of Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Originals restricted. Use microfilm copy only.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 4233109
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
John Howell Books, purchase, 1948.
Collection previously in the libraries of Robert Ernest Cowan and T.W. Norris.
Biography
Halleck, Peachy & Billings was one of the leading San Francisco law firms in the settlement of titles to Mexican land grants; Frederick Billings arrived in San Francisco in 1849; he immediately established a law practice, and soon formed a partnership with Archibald C. Peachy; Peachy later became a member of the California State Assembly in 1852, and of the State Senate in 1860 and 1862; Henry Wager Halleck graduated in engineering from West point, participated in the Mexican War, and later prepared a report on California land titles; became an active member of the California Constitutional Convention; he resigned from the army and joined the law firm in 1854, compiling his books: The mining laws of Spain and Mexico, and International law; returned to the U.S. Army in 1860, later becoming a general during the Civil War; the firm was dissolved in 1861.
Scope and Content
Collection contains correspondence, mainly relating to land litigation of Halleck, Peachy & Billings, with documents and diseños (originals, copies, and translations) used in the settlement of the claims. Also contains papers in various legal cases, some concerning ships, Chinese immigration and the San Francisco funding bill, as well as a few accounts and some tax records. Includes files on the settlement of the William Alexander Leidesdorff and Joseph L. Folsom estates. Contains a small group of correspondence and papers relating to Henry Wager Halleck's military career, 1847-56, and manuscript drafts and notes for his History of California.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Halleck, H.W. (Henry Wager), 1815-1872--Archives.; Halleck, Peachy & Billings (Firm)--Archives.; Law firms--California--San Francisco--Archival resources.
Partial Index to Correspondents in Collection
Alsop & Chauncey letter to: Box 6, folder 15
Bahneberg, Mr. Box 6, folder 16, 18
Barnes, James Box 6, folder 20
Barron, William E. Box 4, folders 1, 2
Barron, Forbes & Company letter to: Box 4, folder 1
Billings, Frederick Box 1, folders 2, 3; Box 4, folder 1
Bradford, A.C. Box 1, folder 4
Bradley, Mr. letter to: Box 6, folder 20
Brannan, Samuel Box 6, folder 6
Burch, John Chilton Box 4, folder 2
Calverwell, Stephen L. Box 6, folder 20
Carillo, Anastasio Box 1, folder 6
Carter, Bernard Box 1, folder 6
Cross & Company Box 1, folder 6
Crowell, William H. Box 1, folder 6
de la Rosa, Luis Box 6, folder 15
Duncan, Sherman & Company Box 6, folder 18; letter to: Box 6, folder 14
Dupuy, A. Box 6, folder 15
Durfee & Myers Box 6, folder 20
Ender, E. Box 4, folder 2
Folsom, Joseph Box 6, folder 13, 14; letter to: Box 6, folders 15-18
Forbes, Alexander Box 4, folder 2
Forbes, James Alexander Box 4, folder 2; Box 6, folder 6
Forrest, S.T. Box 6, folder 19
Fourgeaud, V.J. Box 6, folder 17
Goodhue & Company letter to: Box 4, folder 1
Grannis, G.W. memoranda: Box 5, folder 1
Gray, J.B. Box 4, folder 2
Grim, A.K. Box 1, folder 6
Guerrero, Francisco Box 6, folder 2; letter to: Box 6, folder 1
Gwin, William M. letters to: Box 4, folder 2; Box 6, folder 20
Halleck, Henry Wager Box 4, folder 1; Box 6, folder 15
Hansen [governor-general] letter to: Box 6, folder 13
Hardie, James A. Box 1, folder 6
Harrison, John Box 6, folder 18
Hendricks, Thomas Box 1, folder 6; Box 6, folder 20
Hennen, Duncan Box 6, folder 19
Hill, Richard letter to: Box 6, folder 15
Humphreys, Joshua J. Box 1, folder 6
Huse, Charles E. Box 1, folder 6
Inge, Samuel William Box 6, folder 19
Jesup, Thomas Sidney letter to: Box 6, folder 14
Larkin, Thomas Oliver Box 6, folder 3
Latham, Milton S. Box 1, folder 1; letter to: Box 4, folder 2
Latham & Aldrich letter to: Box 6, folder 14
Leidesdorff, William Alexander Box 6, folder 1; letters to: Box 6, folders 2-6
Loomis, Charles Box 1, folder 6
Mackay, J. Box 1, folder 6
Mackay, W.R. Isaacs Box 1, folder 6
McMurray, R.O. Box 1, folder 5
Marcy, William Learned letter to: Box 6, folder 1
Meredith, I.W.S. Box 6, folder 20
Miner & Haynes Box 1, folder 6
Montgomery, John B. Box 6, folder 4
Morgan, John Box 6, folder 18
Morrison, James Box 6, folder 20
Müller, C. Box 6, folder 15
O'Connor, Cornelius Box 6, folder 20
Olmstead, Horace Box 6, folder 20
Naglee, Henry M. Box 1, folder 6
Pairo, A.W. Box 1, folder 6
Parrott, Juan Box 6, folder 15
Peralta, Antonio Maria Box 6, folder 6
Pickett, Mr. Box 6, folder 17
Revere, Joseph Warren Box 6, folder 6
Robinson, J.P. Box 1, folder 6
Rogers, Mrs. Letter to: Box 6, folder 13
Rogers, D. Box 6, folder 15-17
Rogers, S.R. Box 6, folder 16
Sanders & Brenham Box 6, folder 19
Scott, Charles L. letter to: Box 4, folder 2
Sherman, Edwin A. Box 6, folder 20
Sherwood, John Box 6, folder 18; letter to: Box 6, folder 15
Smith, James Broom Box 1, folder 6
Smith, S.A. Box 1, folder 1
Smith, Stephen Box 6, folder 5
Snydam, Reed & Company Box 6, folders 15-19; letters to: Box 6, folders 13, 14, 16-17
Southall, A.G. Box 1, folder 6
Stimson, Robert J. Box 6, folder 19
Suter, Lee & Company Box 6, folder 19
Sutter, John Augustus Box 6, folder 6
Taliaferro, Alfred W. Box 1, folder 6
Wakeman, A.C. letter to: Box 6, folder 19
Watson, J.R. Box 1, folder 6
Wilson, James B. Box 1, folder 6; Box 6, folder 20
Wise, Tully R. Box 4, folder 2
Woodliff, Thomas Box 6, folder 20
Yale, Gregory Box 4, folder 1; Box 6, folder 20 letters to: Box 4, folders 1-2
Young, P.R. Box 6, folder 20
Related Material
Halleck, Peachy & Billings correspondence and papers (Collection 102). Available at Department of Special Collections, UCLA.
Container List
- Various Cases
  - Letters from Halleck, Peachy, & Billings to various persons, 1855-60., (3 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters from Frederick Billings to Alfred Barstow, 1866-69., (24 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Frederick Billings - papers relating to his official appointments, 1848-55., (14 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters from A.C. Bradford to Halleck, Peachy & Billings, 1857-58., (9 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters from R.O. McMurray to Halleck, Peachy and Billings, 1851-53., (14 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters from various persons to Halleck, Peachy & Billings, 1849-60., (34 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - City of San Francisco: claim to Pueblo Lands, prosecuted before the Land Commission - correspondence and papers, 1834-54., (16 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - John A. Sutter, Jr: sale of Sacramento property to Archibald Peachy - papers, 1839, 1848-49., (5 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Mary H. Machett vs. Stephen W. Tichenor - correspondence and papers, 1842-52., (7 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - U. S. Marine Hospital, Rincon Point - correspondence relating to, 1847-57., (25 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Alcalde Levanworth: grants of San Francisco property - papers, 1849-52., (6 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henry Hill vs. Charles Botts - correspondence and papers, 1849-55., (16 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Henry Hill vs. Charles Botts - correspondence and papers, 1856-59., (25 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Thomas W. Hardy estate - correspondence and papers, 1850-68., (19 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Street assessment cases, San Francisco - papers, 1851 and n.d., (16 pieces) (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Daniel C. Callahan, property in Sacramento - mortgages and other papers, 1851-62., (26 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Joaquin Carrillo et al., claimants for Rancho Llano de Santa Rosa - papers, 1852-60., (5 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Rancho Jesus Maria: claim of John G. Parish, James M. Harkin, et al. - papers, 1854-55., (13 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Rancho La Visitacion Cañada de Guadalupe y Rodeo Viejo, 1854-59., (4 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Rancho Refugio: claim of Juan and Francisco Bolcoff [no.214 (Land Commission)] - papers, ca. 1855., (4 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Noah E. Smith vs. William F. Roelofson, involving the latter's interest in the Union Mining and Trading Company, Starr, Binsley & Company, Sacramento, and F. Vassault & Company, San Francisco - depositions on Roelofson's behalf and other papers, 1855-56., (11 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - William A. Pfeiffer - mortgage papers, 1855-60., (6 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - C. Morrill vs. G.R. Garretson: reclamation against Garretson's account - correspondence and papers, 1856-59., (6 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Grant Hudson vs. Northern et al. - depositions and testimony, 1856-59., (1 vol.) (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - David C. Broderick estate: claims of David Hawkes Broderick and John Broderick - correspondence and papers, 1856-60., (8 pieces) (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Accounts, notes, receipts, etc., 1849-60., (22 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Articles and reports relating to land titles, land law, transportation and trade in sparsely settled areas of the West, mining claims, and a list of a U.S. Grand Jury in San Francisco., (16 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Various Legal Matters Handled by Halleck, Peachy & Billings
    - Correspondence and papers, 1851-58., (47 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence and papers, 1859-61 and n.d., (21 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Journals, n.d., (2 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Land Claims - Memoranda and Abstracts, Chiefly in Halleck's Handwriting, Transactions ca. 1835-55, no.1-172
    (Some numbers missing)
    - no.1-54., (50 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - no.55-100., (45 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - no.101-172., (45 pieces) (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Almaden Claim, 1848-60
  - Halleck, Peachy & Billings - letters sent, 1858-60., (31 pieces) (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Letters between, various persons, including some to Halleck, Peachy & Billings, 1848-60., (13 pieces) (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Legal papers concerning the case, 1847-59., (16 pieces) (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Argument for the claim - manuscript draft., (253 pieces) (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Argument for the claim - manuscript draft of the printed argument., (12 pieces) (Box 4, Folder 5)
- The William Alexander Leidesdorff & Joseph Libbey Folsom Estates
  - G.W. Granniss. Memorandum relating to the Leidesdorff Estate., (2 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Working Papers of Halleck, Peachy & Billings Regarding the Settlement of the Two Estates, Containing, Manuscript Notes, etc.
    - 1850-51., (18 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1851-56., (29 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1857-63., (24 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Legal Documents, Agreements, etc., Concerning the two Estates
    - 1847-50., (37 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1851., (15 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1852., (12 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1853-54., (7 pieces) (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Papers Concerning the Leidesdorff Estate
  - Correspondence
    - Letters from William A. Leidesdorff to various persons, 1846-47., (2 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Letters from Francisco Guerrero to Leidesdorff, 1846., (3 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Letters from Thomas Oliver Larkin to Leidesdorff, 1845-46., (2 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Letters from John B. Montgomery to Leidesdorff, 1846., (5 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Letters from Stephen Smith to Leidesdorff, 1847-48., (4 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Letters from various persons to Leidesdorff, 1846-48., (5 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Legal Documents
    - 1854-55., (17 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - 1856-59., (12 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Accounts and Bills, Mainly Relating to the Leidesdorff Estate
    - 1841-47., (27 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1848., (65 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - 1849., (47 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1850-51 and n.d., (21 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Papers Concerning the Folsom Estate
  - Letters from Joseph L. Folsom to Various Persons
    - 1849-51., (14 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - 1852-54., (6 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Letters from Various Persons to Joseph L. Folsom
    - 1849-June 1851., (14 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - July-December 1851., (13 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - 1852-53., (8 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - 1854-55., (14 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Letters Received by Halleck. Peachy, and P. Warren Van Winkle, Executors of the Estate, Relating to its Administration
    - 1850-56., (12 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - 1857-62., (12 pieces) (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - American and Union Theaters, San Francisco
    - Correspondence, 1852-55., (5 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Legal papers, 1854-55., (13 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Legal papers, 1856 and n.d., (13 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Folsom as Assistant Quarter Master, San Francisco: Settlement of Accounts
    - Papers, 1847-52., (38 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Tehama House Boarding House. San Francisco: Papers and Accounts
    - 1852., (47 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1853-54., (38 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1855 and n.d., (36 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Settlement of the Folsom Estate: Bills and Accounts
    - 1848-51., (61 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1852-53., (58 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1854., (42 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1855., (78 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1856-60 and n.d., (25 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - City, State and County taxes - various lists, 1851/52-1855/56., (11 pieces) (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Account books, 1852-55, 1871-77., (4 volumes) (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Empty strong-box (with key) which originally contained part of the Halleck, Peachy, and Billings papers. (Box 8)